Every good thing in this world started with a dream.
Wonka is a comedy, family, fantasy film directed by Paul King.
Willy Wonka – chock-full of ideas and determined to change the world one delectable bite at a time – is proof that the best
things in life begin with a dream, and if you’re lucky enough to meet Willy Wonka, anything is possible.
Willy Wonka, played by Timothée Chalamet.
Noodle, played by Calah Lane.
Chief of Police, played by Keegan-Michael Key.
Oompa Loompa, played by Hugh Grant.
Arthur Slugworth, played by Paterson Joseph.
Mrs. Scrubbit, played by Olivia Colman.
Wonka is a 2023 musical fantasy film directed by Paul King,
who co-wrote the screenplay with Simon Farnaby.
It is a prequel to the 1964 novel Charlie and the
Chocolate Factory by Roald Dahl.
The film stars Timothée Chalamet as Willy Wonka and also features Calah Lane, Keegan-Michael Key, Paterson Joseph,
Matt Lucas, Mathew Baynton, Sally Hawkins, Rowan Atkinson, Jim Carter, Olivia Colman, and Hugh Grant.
It portrays Willy Wonka's early days as a chocolatier
while contending with his future rivals.
Development began when Warner Bros.
Pictures reacquired the film rights to the character in October 2016
and announced that the film would be an origin story.
The film tells an original story and was developed by King to exist as a "companion piece" to the film Willy Wonka & the
Chocolate Factory by reprising some of the music, thematic elements, and the visual design of the Oompa Loompas.
In May 2021, Chalamet was confirmed to portray Wonka, and the
supporting cast was announced in September of that year.
Filming began in the United Kingdom in September, at Warner Bros.
Studios Leavesden in Watford, as well as Oxford, Lyme Regis, Bath, St
Albans, and at the Rivoli Ballroom in Crofton Park, London.
The film's original songs were written by Neil Hannon and its
original score was composed by Joby Talbot.
Wonka premiered in London at the Royal Festival Hall, Southbank Centre
on November 28, 2023, and was released by Warner Bros.
Pictures in the United Kingdom on December 8, and in
the United States on December 15.
The film received generally positive reviews from critics, who praised Chalamet's performance and the film's presentation, and was a box-office
success, grossing over $634 million worldwide against a $125 million budget, to become the eighth-highest-grossing film of 2023.
It received a nomination for the BAFTA Award for Outstanding British Film and Chalamet was
nominated for a Golden Globe Award for Best Actor in a Motion Picture – Musical or Comedy.
A sequel is in development.
The film explores themes of chocolate, musical,
prequel, nostalgic, duringcreditsstinger.
The tone is lighthearted.